It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s time for the
NutritionFacts Grab Bag,
where we look at the science
behind a whole array of topics.
And we start with how the adverse
effects of industrial pollutants
in seafood may counteract
the benefits of nutrients in fish.
Although the levels
of industrial pollutants,
like dioxins and PCBs,
continue to decline
in the food supply,
there is one dietary source
that still remains
a major threat: fish.
Everything eventually flows
into the sea.
Yes, we can get some dioxins
from eating horses,
but most of our exposure
comes from eating fish.
The U.S. Environmental
Protection Agency
puts the tolerable upper limit
of dioxin intake
per kilogram of body weight
at 0.7 picograms—
less than one trillionth
of a gram— per day.
We're already skirting the max
by just consuming dairy,
and fish takes us
right over the top,
even at low levels
of consumption.
So, the adverse effects
of chemical contaminants
in seafood may counteract
the benefits
of any nutrients in fish.
So much so
that many dietary guidelines
recommend no more than
one serving a week of fish
and seafood to cut down
on exposure
to toxic pollutants.
But which is worse?
Wild-caught or farmed?
Take salmon for example.
Salmon had the highest toxic
equivalents of PCBs,
followed by canned tuna,
as well as the highest
neurotoxic equivalents of PCBs.
If you compare the levels
of PCBs in salmon
farmed in Maine and Canada,
versus salmon
wild-caught in Alaska,
versus organically farmed salmon
from Norway,
compared
to the wild-caught salmon,
the farmed salmon,
organic or otherwise,
had significantly higher
PCB levels.
This appears to extend
to other contaminants too.
Based on the testing
of literally tons
of salmon samples
from around the world,
for every toxin
the researchers tested,
the samples of farmed salmon
had higher levels than
did the wild-caught salmon—
higher levels of DDT and
these other banned pesticides.
Over 10 times more PCBs
in farmed salmon;
over 10 times more dioxins.
In order to not exceed
EPA safety levels,
we wouldn't want to eat
supermarket salmon
more than once every two weeks
in Denver or New Orleans,
more than once a month in LA,
Vancouver, DC, Seattle,
Chicago, or New York,
just once every two months
in Edinburgh, Paris,
London, Oslo, Boston,
San Francisco, or Toronto,
and just a few times a year
in Frankfurt, Germany.
We can track pollutants
from the ocean to the table,
and it's through the fish oil.
The fish oil used in the feed
for farmed fish
transfers pollutants
to the fish themselves,
and then the fish carries the
pollutants to human consumers.
So, yes, salmon has
the healthy omega-3 fatty acids,
but they also contain
high levels of toxic chemicals,
and not just the PCBs,
dioxins, and pesticides.
Farmed salmon test positive
for antibiotic residues,
higher levels of forever
chemicals, and flame retardants,
and also test positive for
endocrine disrupting compounds—
hormone disruptors like BPA.
Something you don't see
in samples of sea vegetables
like seaweed, presumably because
of their low fat content.
Farmed salmon may also
have higher levels of mercury
than wild-caught,
though the opposite may be
the case for farmed tuna.
Arsenic also goes both ways,
with more arsenic
in wild seabream
compared to farmed,
but less in wild seabass.
However, all the arsenic levels
were bad,
exceeding
cancer benchmark values
indicating a moderate risk of cancer
due to fish consumption.
Some analyses have
found dioxin and PCB levels
similar across the board,
but, in general,
you can think of aquaculture
fish as "farmed and dangerous"
compared to wild-caught
in terms of higher
levels of most pollutants.
So, that's why researchers
emphasize the importance
of labeling as a means
to help consumers
avoid unnecessary exposure
to highly contaminated fish.
Unfortunately,
mislabeling is rampant.
So, the farmed versus
wild-caught question
may be largely academic
given the extent
of seafood fraud
and mislabeling.
An investigation
by the New York Attorney General
found that consumers
who bought what was advertised
as "wild" salmon
actually often received
farm-raised salmon instead.
Up to 43 percent
of salmon tested
across the United States,
for example, were mislabeled,
most commonly passing off
farmed salmon as wild-caught.
In our next story,
NutritionFacts.org
Senior Research Scientist
Dr. Kristine Dennis joins us
with a fascinating look at how
turmeric extract supplements
can cause liver injury.
Liver injury associated
with turmeric:
Ten cases from the Drug-Induced
Liver Injury Network
in the United States,
and there are others too,
including three cases
reported in Australia
and a series reported to
the Italian Ministry of Health.
Is turmeric really
a new hepatotoxic substance?
First of all, regardless of what
the titles of the papers say,
these cases appear to be from
turmeric extract supplements,
rather than turmeric the spice.
It's like green tea
and green tea extract pills.
Brewed green tea appears
to be completely safe
for the liver,
but give people green
tea extract supplements,
and the livers of as many as
1 in 17 people becomes inflamed.
So, we should consume
our green tea in beverage form,
not pill form,
and similarly,
our turmeric in spice form
at culinary doses,
not capsules,
unless they contain
just a single ingredient:
whole spice turmeric,
not curcumin,
not an extract,
no other ingredients.
While turmeric extract
supplements
have a relatively safe
side-effect profile
even at high doses,
there is an increasing number
of case reports linking them
to liver injury,
especially when combined
with agents such as piperine,
a compound found
in black pepper.
As we've covered before,
compounds like piperine
are added to turmeric
to enhance the
bioavailability of curcumin,
potentially contributing
to its toxicity,
as one reason curcumin may be so
safe is that it is poorly absorbed.
As we have cautioned before,
piperine blocks
liver detox enzymes
that can make some substances
like curcumin more potent.
And turmeric curcumin
supplement formulations
with high bioavailability,
such as nanoformulations
or those with added piperine,
have been less investigated.
There is a mistaken assumption
that if a little is good,
then more must be better.
We'd never make
that assumption for drugs,
so why is it made
for supplements?
In this case, more does not
necessarily mean better.
A review of nearly a hundred
randomized controlled trials
of turmeric or
curcumin supplements
for nonalcoholic
fatty liver disease
found that they successfully
calmed liver inflammation.
And guess
which worked better?
Low-dose supplements
worked about 10 times better
than high-dose ones.
There are caveats, though,
even for whole food turmeric.
As Dr. Greger
has covered before,
people who have a tendency
to form kidney stones
should be careful
due to turmeric's relatively
high oxalate content.
Dr. Greger recommends
only a quarter teaspoon a day
in his Daily Dozen.
There's also been concern
about lead contamination
of the whole food spice.
Lead chromate
has been used
to make turmeric appear
more yellow in Bangladesh,
where much of turmeric sold in
the United States is imported from,
leading to multiple recalls.
The wonderful news is
food safety policies can work!
Since the original paper
of lead chromate contamination
in turmeric from Bangladesh,
the portion
of market turmeric samples
with detectable lead
went from about 50 percent
to zero.
Unfortunately, there is still
more work to be done, though.
In four South Asian countries
where more than 80 percent
of the world's turmeric
is produced,
14 percent of samples had
detectable lead above 2 ug/g.
For context,
this is 20 times higher
than the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration's
maximum allowable level
for lead in candy.
And some stores
sold turmeric
containing much higher levels
of lead
that would result
in projected blood lead levels
in children up to
10 times higher
than the U.S. Centers
for Disease Control's
threshold for concern.
This is a reminder that just
because something is natural
doesn't mean
it can't cause harm.
Turmeric dietary supplements
are big business,
estimated to account
for $69 million in sales
in the United States alone.
Though its popularity does help
put the recent spate
of liver toxicity
cases in context.
More than 10 million people
in the United States
take turmeric
or curcumin supplements.
So, that would be like
one case in a million.
Some people may just be more
susceptible genetically—
7 of the 10 patients
in this case series
had a genetic variant
that's relatively rare
in the general population.
Still, it's safer for
everyone to use the real thing
and not some extract
in some supplement.
And please don't let anyone
inject turmeric or curcumin
into your veins.
Finally today,
we look at how pawpaw
fruits contain neurotoxins
that may cause a
neurodegenerative disease.
Yikes.
The pawpaw
is the largest fruit
native to North America,
weighing up
to two pounds (1 kg).
Pawpaws taste like
a mixture of bananas,
mangos, and pineapples.
They're like a tropical
banana-mango custard,
but found in
temperate forests
across the eastern
United States,
nourishing humankind
for thousands of years
and now complete with
their own pawpaw festivals.
Papayas are
sometimes called pawpaws,
but they're
completely different fruits.
The real pawpaw is
also known as the dog banana,
false-banana,
Indian banana,
prairie banana,
poor man's banana,
Ozark banana,
Banango (I like that one),
Indiana banana
(has a nice ring to it, too),
and the Kentucky banana.
Pawpaws are my
favorite fruit,
or, should I say,
were my favorite fruit.
One of the reasons
that I moved to rural Virginia
was because the property
had a whole grove
of pawpaw trees.
I was going to be
set for life.
That is, until I ate
a few too many
on the first harvest,
became quite ill,
and actually looked them up.
Pro tip: in the future,
look to see if a food is toxic
before you eat lots of it.
Little did I know,
the pawpaw belonged
to an infamous
family of fruits
that contain three different
types of neurotoxins.
I had actually done
a video, years ago,
warning people
not to eat soursop,
also known as graviola,
but didn't realize
pawpaws were related.
The family includes
soursop, guanabana, sweetsop,
sugar apple, cherimoya,
and custard-apple,
which are all linked to
a neurodegenerative disease
called progressive
supranuclear palsy,
which is like a
treatment-resistant Parkinson's,
with hallucinations,
widespread brain atrophy,
and dementia.
And consumption
of these fruits
is associated with
about 20 times the odds
of having this kind of
atypical Parkinson's syndrome.
Expose rats to even
a fraction of the dose
the people were exposed to,
and they develop the same
kind of brain lesions
you see on autopsy
in human victims.
And, in several patients who
stopped consuming these fruits,
the progression
of their condition ceased,
and, in one patient,
the symptoms even disappeared
after a change in diet.
There is an urgent need
to raise public awareness
about the neurotoxicity
of this family of fruits,
which are often,
ironically, praised
for their taste
and medicinal values.
In fact, you can find
dietary supplements
containing these plants,
promoted for their
purported anticancer effects.
And a soursop extract
can inhibit cancer cell growth
in a petri dish,
but only at concentrations
much higher than the amount
that kills off brain cells.
Even a low
cumulative consumption
may worsen disease severity
and cognitive deficits
in degenerative
Parkinson's type disease,
as in 0.2 fruit-years.
So, that's just one-fifth
of a fruit a day for a year,
or a single fruit a month
for six years,
or just one fruit a year
throughout your entire life.
The bottom line
is that these fruit
could contribute
to the development
of degenerative
parkinsonism in humans,
and so, as a precaution,
more restrictive public health
preventive recommendations
should be made
regarding their consumption.
So, okay, consumption
of these tropical fruits
potentially constitutes
a serious public health problem,
but what about pawpaws?
So, why aren't
pawpaw eaters getting sick?
Well, it's only ripe
for a few weeks a year,
so, unlike the tropical fruit
that can be eaten year-round,
people may not have
a lot of exposure to them.
Fresh pawpaws aren't really
even sold commercially, either,
since they bruise so easily,
but now the fruit's
available in any season,
sold as frozen pulp or jam,
and there are
supplements out there too.
Not to mention,
if you're like me,
trees in your backyard.
When the U.S. Food and Drug
Administration was asked about them,
they noted that pawpaw
has a long history of food use,
and it didn't have any evidence
that the fruit was unsafe to eat.
You'll hear things like this:
"Currently,
there have been no reports
of neurogenerative diseases
linked to the consumption
of the pawpaw fruit,"
until, of course, there are.
"Progressive supranuclear
palsy and pawpaw."
Poor guy had trouble
speaking and walking
as his brain
was atrophying in his skull.
Tragically he actually died
before they figured it out,
but his wife disclosed
that they owned pawpaw trees,
and he had been
eating dozens a year.
And when researchers
started looking,
they indeed seemed
to find a link between
this neurodegenerative disease
and pawpaw consumption
in the United States.
So, alas,
no more pawpaws for me.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.